Arabic: وسط هذه الطبيعة الخلابة وعلى بعد تسعة كيلومترات جنوب
مدينة عفرين،
English Translation: Amidst this breathtaking nature, and
nine kilometers south of the city of Afrin,
Arabic: تقع بلدة باصوطة، إحدى أجمل القرى والبلدات في منطقة
عفرين.
English Translation: lies the town of Basouta, one of the
most beautiful villages and towns in the Afrin region.
Arabic: تتميز باصوطة بهوائها النقي ومائها الوفير،
English Translation: Basouta is characterized by its pure
air and abundant water,
Arabic: حيث يمر في البلدة نهر عفرين،
English Translation: as the Afrin River flows through the
town.
Arabic: كما يوجد فيها نبع ماء غزير، نابع من أسفل جبل ليلون،
English Translation: It also has a copious water spring
flowing from the foot of Mount Layloun,
Arabic: وتحيط بها وبمنازلها البساتين المثمرة.
English Translation: and it is surrounded, along with its
houses, by fruitful orchards.
Arabic: خيو بلدة الباصوطة، بلدة قديمة يعني، يعني كتير قديمة.
English Translation: Brother, the town of Basouta is an old
town, I mean, very old.
Arabic: تابعة لمركز عفرين، وتبعد عن عفرين 9 كيلو متر قبلي
عفرين يعني بتقع.
English Translation: It belongs to the center of Afrin, and
is about 9 kilometers south of Afrin.
Arabic: ضيعة بتشتهر بطبيعتها الخلابة الجميلة.
English Translation: It is a village famous for its
beautiful, breathtaking nature.
Arabic: طبعاً الطبيعة هي بتعود لكثرة المي، لكثرة الخضار.
English Translation: Of course, this nature is due to the
abundance of water and greenery.
Arabic: أهاليها بيشتغلوا يعني قبل هلق 200، 250 سنة اعتمادهم
على تربية المواشي.
English Translation: Its residents worked, I mean about 200
or 250 years ago, relying on raising livestock.
Arabic: في بعض الزراعات كان، في الرمان كانت تشتهر فيها
باصوطة.
English Translation: There were some crops; Basouta was
famous for pomegranates.
Arabic: يعني تقريباً تاريخ الرمان بيعود إلى 200، 250 سنة،
يعني رمان الباصوطة رمان مشهور.
English Translation: The history of pomegranates there goes
back about 200 to 250 years, so Basouta's pomegranates are
famous.
Arabic: في عنا نبعة، نبعة الباصوطة، نبعة راس النبع.
English Translation: We have a spring, the Basouta spring,
the spring of Ras Al-Nabe'.
Arabic: النبعة هي كمان يعني بيعتبر من أكبر النبعات تقريباً
بمحافظة حلب ومنطقة عفرين يعني.
English Translation: This spring is considered one of the
largest springs in the Aleppo governorate and the Afrin
region.
Arabic: بتشتهر بميتها العذبة يعني، والعالم بيعتمدوا عليها
بري المزروعات والأراضي.
English Translation: It is famous for its sweet water, and
people rely on it to irrigate crops and lands.
Arabic: عدد سكانها بحوالي 4000، طبعاً في عنا نسبة من اخواننا
العرب يعني تقريبا بحدود 25 بالمية يعني.
English Translation: Its population is around 4000. Of
course, we have a percentage of our Arab brothers, about 25
percent.
Arabic: بتشتهر بقلعتها، قلعة الباصوطة يلي تاريخها تاريخ قديم
يعني، يعني بتعود لعهد الأيوبيين.
English Translation: It is famous for its castle, the
Basouta Castle, which has an ancient history, dating back to
the Ayyubid era.
Arabic: فيها مي كتير، هلق بالمرحلة الأخيرة هي من 50 سنة إنت
وجاي،
English Translation: It has a lot of water. Now, in recent
times, from 50 years ago until now,
Arabic: اعتمدوا على زراعة الفاكهة يعني، الفواكه بشكل عام، إن
كان دراق، تفاح، جانرك، خوخ.
English Translation: they have relied on planting fruit
trees, fruits in general, whether it's peaches, apples,
green plums, or plums.
Arabic: بتبعد عن محافظة حلب عن طريق عفرين بحدود حوالي 60
كيلو متر.
English Translation: It is about 60 kilometers away from the
Aleppo governorate via Afrin.
Arabic: تعد منطقة عفرين إحدى المناطق القديمة في ريف حلب،
English Translation: The Afrin region is considered one of
the ancient regions in the countryside of Aleppo,
Arabic: وتعد بلدة الباصوطة من أقدم القرى والبلدات في عفرين،
English Translation: and the town of Basouta is one of the
oldest villages and towns in Afrin,
Arabic: حيث يعود تاريخها لآلاف السنين.
English Translation: as its history dates back thousands of
years.
Arabic: وللتعرف على أصل تسمية البلدة ومعناها، لابد من لقاء
الأهالي وسؤالهم عن ذلك.
English Translation: To find out the origin and meaning of
the town's name, we must meet the locals and ask them about
it.
Arabic: حقيقة باصوطة هي من إحدى القرى القديمة جداً في منطقة
عفرين.
English Translation: Actually, Basouta is one of the very
ancient villages in the Afrin region.
Arabic: طبعاً منطقة عفرين كلها قديمة يعني وفي آثار بتدلل على
قدمها التاريخي من، يعني بيعود إلى آلاف السنين.
English Translation: Of course, the entire Afrin region is
old, and there are ruins proving its historical antiquity,
which dates back thousands of years.
Arabic: ولكن قرية باصوطة إحدى القرى القديمة جداً.
English Translation: But the village of Basouta is one of
the very ancient villages.
Arabic: في أكتر من قرية تبدأ بكلمة "با"، يعني متل باصوطة،
باصلحايا، باصمرا، بابليت.
English Translation: There is more than one village that
starts with the word "Ba", like Basouta, Baselhaya, Basamra,
Bableet.
Arabic: أنا رجعت لعدة مراجع، في مرجع بيقول أنه كلمة با تبدأ
يعني هي دلالة مكانية.
English Translation: I checked several sources, and one
source says that the word "Ba" indicates a spatial
reference.
Arabic: يعني متل بابليت، يعني مكان المستنقع، هيك معناها.
English Translation: Like Bableet, for example, means the
place of the swamp.
Arabic: ولكن نحن عنا باللغة الكردية الـ"با" يعني الهواء.
English Translation: However, in our Kurdish language, "Ba"
means wind.
Arabic: نحن إذا فسرناها على هالتفسير يعني بتكون باصوطة
معناها الهواء الحارق أو الساخن جداً يعني.
English Translation: If we interpret it this way, Basouta
means the burning or very hot wind.
Arabic: فالأرجح أنه يبدو كان المنطقة يجيها هواء، يعني هاد
الوادي كان يجي هواء من هواء ساخن يعني.
English Translation: It is most likely that the area used to
receive wind, meaning this valley used to get a hot wind.
Arabic: الأرجح أنه يكون باصوطة معناها الهواء الساخن يعني.
English Translation: It is most likely that the meaning of
Basouta is the hot wind.
Arabic: لبلدة باصوطة تاريخ حافل، حيث مر عليها العديد من
العصور القديمة،
English Translation: The town of Basouta has a rich history,
having gone through many ancient eras,
Arabic: التي خلفت العديد من الآثار والمعالم،
English Translation: which left behind many ruins and
landmarks.
Arabic: ولعل أشهرها نبع باصوطة وقلعة باصوطة الأثرية،
English Translation: Perhaps the most famous of these are
the Basouta Spring and the ancient Basouta Castle,
Arabic: التي بني على أنقاضها جزء من منازل البلدة،
English Translation: upon whose ruins a part of the town's
houses was built,
Arabic: والتي كانت مركزاً مهماً في أوائل القرن التاسع عشر.
English Translation: and which was an important center in
the early 19th century.
Arabic: حقيقة منطقة عفرين هي منطقة قديمة جداً.
English Translation: In reality, the Afrin region is a very
ancient region.
Arabic: الآثار فيها بتدلل أنه هي من آلاف السنين، يعني في
آثار بتدلل على أنه 3000 سنة قبل الميلاد.
English Translation: The ruins there indicate that it dates
back thousands of years, meaning there are ruins dating back
to 3000 BC.
Arabic: في قلاع وحصون تدلل، وفي معبد كتير كبير مهم هون.
English Translation: There are castles and fortresses
proving this, and there is a very large and important temple
here.
Arabic: قرية باصوطة هي من هي القرى القديمة جداً، ولها قلعة،
هي القلعة بتدلل، هي بقايا قلعة.
English Translation: The village of Basouta is one of these
very ancient villages, and it has a castle; this castle is
proof, it's the ruins of a castle.
Arabic: حقيقة هي القلعة نحن رجعنا لمراجع، أنه قلعة الباصوطة
من 1600، 1601 بتاريخ 1601 جرت فيها ملحمة كتير كبيرة، كان
فيها معركة كبيرة وكان فيها بطل يعني.
English Translation: Actually, regarding this castle, we
checked sources which state that the Basouta Castle, around
1600 or 1601, in 1601, witnessed a very great epic, a major
battle, and there was a hero.
Arabic: اسمه بطال يا بطال يعني.
English Translation: His name was Battal.
Arabic: فهي الملحمة الأكراد دونوها في تراثهم، في أغانيهم
يعني.
English Translation: The Kurds recorded this epic in their
heritage, in their songs.
Arabic: فانذكرت يعني وكان في بطل، أحد أبطال المنطقة خاض حروب
يعني.
English Translation: It was mentioned, and there was a hero,
one of the region's heroes, who fought wars.
Arabic: ولذلك نحن عودة إلى هذا التراث وتاريخ القلعة، منقول
أنه بلدة باصوطة من البلدات القديمة جداً يعني.
English Translation: Therefore, returning to this heritage
and the history of the castle, we say that the town of
Basouta is one of the very ancient towns.
Arabic: يتميز أهالي باصوطة الذين بلغ عددهم حوالي الأربعة
آلاف نسمة،
English Translation: The residents of Basouta, whose
population reached about four thousand people,
Arabic: وجلهم من الأكراد باللباس الكردي الخاص،
English Translation: mostly Kurds, are distinguished by
their special Kurdish attire,
Arabic: حيث غلب على أهالي البلدة الطابع الكردي باللباس
والعادات والتقاليد.
English Translation: as the Kurdish character has prevailed
among the town's residents in dress, customs, and
traditions.
بالنسبة للرجل كانوا يلبسوا السراويل
For men, they used to wear trousers.
والصرماية الحمرا هاي العتيقة
And these old red shoes,
ويحطوا على راسهم شال ويعملوا كوفية منها
and put a shawl on their head and make a keffiyeh out of it.
أما بالنسبة للنسوان فاللباس الكردي معروف طويل وإلو زمة من
هون يعني معروف إنه فستان كردي هذا
As for women, the Kurdish dress is known to be long with a
gather here, it's known to be a Kurdish dress.
تشابهت عادات وتقاليد الأهالي هنا مع جيرانهم، أهالي القرى
والبلدات المجاورة
The customs and traditions of the people here matched those
of their neighbors in the adjacent villages and towns,
حيث تميزت أعراس أهالي قرية باصوطة بالأغاني والموسيقى
والدبكات الكردية، كما عرف أهلها بالحب والكرم.
where the weddings of the people of Basouta village were
distinguished by Kurdish songs, music, and dabke dances, and
its people were known for their love and generosity.
مراسم الزواج أول ما تبدأ بالخطبة، يعني يتعرفوا على بعضهم،
يبعتوا أهلهم لعند بيت العروس ويخطبوها
Marriage ceremonies first begin with the engagement; they
get to know each other, send their families to the bride's
house, and propose to her.
وبعد منها يتفقوا على الزواج والعرس
After that, they agree on the marriage and the wedding.
وأول ليلة مثلاً كان ليلة الحنة
And the first night, for example, was the henna night.
يتجمعوا أهل الضيعة وقرايبين الطرفين يعني يحتفلوا فيهم
The village people and the relatives of both sides gather to
celebrate them.
وثاني نهار يطالعوها لبيت العريس ويعزموا كل أهل الضيعة
المجاورة وقرايبينهم كمان
The next day, they take her to the groom's house and invite
all the people from the neighboring village and their
relatives as well.
وأحياناً كان يطول العرس شي أسبوع تقريباً، بعدين اختصرت
هالموضوع هذا بالفترة الأخيرة، ما ضل شي يعني حفلات عادية
وبالصالات تقريباً صارت
Sometimes the wedding would last about a week, but recently
this has been shortened. It's just normal parties now,
mostly in halls.
عند زيارتك لأي منطقة كردية لا بد لك إلا وأن تسأل عن أهم طقوس
الأكراد وأحبها على قلوبهم
When visiting any Kurdish area, you must ask about the most
important and beloved Kurdish rituals,
حيث يتميز الأكراد بعيد النيروز الذي يحتفلون فيه ربيع كل عام.
as Kurds are distinguished by the Nowruz festival, which
they celebrate every spring.
نحن عنا طبعا شي خاص فيه، في عنا عيد النوروز، عيد النوروز
كمان إله تاريخ القديم يعني
We obviously have something special, we have the Nowruz
festival, the Nowruz festival also has an ancient history.
العيد هذا بترمز إلى يعني يوم الخلاص، معنى الحرية، معنى اليوم
الجديد يعني
This festival symbolizes the day of salvation, the meaning
of freedom, the meaning of a new day.
يعني كان في ظلم، في اضطهاد، في شب كردي اسمه كان كاوا الحداد،
قضى على هالزلمة وإنه نبهوا الشباب يشعلوا النار
There was injustice, there was oppression. There was a
Kurdish young man named Kawa the Blacksmith, he defeated
this man and told the youth to light a fire.
هذا النار بترمز ليوم الخلاص يوم الحرية يعني
This fire symbolizes the day of salvation, the day of
freedom.
وفرة المياه في البلدة جعلت من الزراعة مصدر رزق أساسي للأهالي
The abundance of water in the town has made agriculture a
primary source of livelihood for the residents.
حيث يعمل الأهالي هنا على الزراعة ويعتمدون على المحاصيل
الزراعية المتنوعة كمصدر أساسي للعيش
The people here work in agriculture and rely on diverse
agricultural crops as a basic source of living.
باصوطة بشكل عام ضيعة زراعية وشعبها كلهم عايشين عالزراعة
Basouta in general is an agricultural village and its people
all live on agriculture.
والزراعة هو أساس بالنسبة للضيعة وباصوطة فيها من جميع أنواع
الفواكه تقريباً اللي موجودة عنا بسوريا
Agriculture is the basis for the village, and Basouta has
almost all types of fruits available here in Syria.
خاصة الرمان، التفاح، السفرجل، ومشمش، وشكربرة، واللوزي،
وغيره، ومن جميع أنواع الفواكه موجودة
Especially pomegranates, apples, quinces, apricots,
shakarpara, almonds, etc. All kinds of fruits are available.
باصوطة شبابها وشعبها شاطرين بالزراعة، يعني اللهم صل عالنبي
فيني أقلك المزارع العادي ما يعادل خبرة المهندس
The youth and people of Basouta are skilled in agriculture.
I mean, blessings upon the Prophet, I can tell you that an
ordinary farmer has the equivalent experience of an
engineer.
السبب جميع الفواكه عم يجيبوها أكتر الأنواع من برا، وخاصة
باصوطة هي الأساس
The reason is that they bring most types of fruits from
outside, and Basouta is specifically the basis.
بيزرعها وبخدمها وبيعطي إنتاج كويس، وبعدين جيراننا الضيع اللي
حوالينا كمان بصير مثلا التطعيم
They plant them, tend to them, and they yield good
production. Then our neighbors, the surrounding villages,
also get into grafting, for example.
النصب بنجيب النصب وبنطعمها وبنعطيها للجيران، كلو بالبيع يعني
بالمصاري، كل شي بالمصاري.
We bring the seedlings, graft them, and give them to
neighbors. All through selling, meaning with money,
everything is for money.
يعني الفواكه عم بتجيب، مثلا التفاح الفرنسي في عنا، البذرة
جاية من فرنسا، الرمان الفرنسي ما كانت عنا، قبل ٣٠، ٤٠ سنة ما
كانت عنا
For example, fruits are brought in. We have French apples,
the seed came from France. We didn't have French
pomegranates 30 or 40 years ago.
هلأ مشهورة كتير مشهورة عنا، وغيرها وغيرها وغيرها، جميع أنواع
الفواكه
Now it's very famous here, and many others, all kinds of
fruits.
مواسمنا أول موسم نحن منبلش فيها تقريباً بأول خمسة، هو موسم
جارنك
Our seasons, the first season we start with is around early
May, which is the green plum season.
طبعاً في شباب الضيعة، في عمال بالضيعة، وأهل الضيعة كلو عندو
بساتين وعندو أراضي، أغلبيتهم عندهم أراضي
Of course, there are the village youth, workers in the
village, and all the village people have orchards and lands,
most of them have lands.
بس قسم كمان منهم ما عندهم أراضي، هدول بيشتغلوا بالزراعة
وكلهم صايرين خبيرين بالزراعة، متلي متلهم متل المهندسين كلهم
باستمرار الخبرة
But a portion of them don't have lands, those work in
agriculture and all of them have become experts in
agriculture. They are like me and like engineers, due to
continuous experience.
إذا بلشنا بالشهر الخامس بإذن الله لشهر طنعش
If we start in the fifth month, God willing, until the
twelfth month.
الجارنك والخوخ وهالشغلات بالخامس بالسادس، بالسابع بنبلش
بالتفاحيات
Green plums, plums, and such things in the fifth and sixth
month. In the seventh, we start with apples.
بعد بالتاسع تقريبا شهرين موسم التفاح، بالتاسع بنبلش بالسفرجل
Then around the ninth month, the apple season lasts for two
months. In the ninth, we start with quinces.
بالعاشر بالرمان والمنجا، والحادي عشر والثاني عشر بالزيتون
In the tenth with pomegranates and mangoes, and the eleventh
and twelfth with olives.
لعل أبرز ما يميز الأكراد هو فنهم، حيث يتواجد الفن أينما
يتواجد الأكراد
Perhaps what most distinguishes Kurds is their art, as art
is present wherever Kurds are.
الذين يحاولون نقل قضيتهم بفنهم، كما تعمل لافا التي تحاول نقل
التراث الكردي
They try to convey their cause through their art, as Lava
does, trying to convey the Kurdish heritage.
من لباس وعادات وتقاليد بلوحاتها الفنية.
From clothing, customs, and traditions through her artistic
paintings.
الفن الكردي هو بشكل عام برسم عن التراث الكردي، بمنطقة عفرين،
يعني بجسد التراث الكردي
Kurdish art, in general, I paint about Kurdish heritage in
the Afrin region, meaning I embody Kurdish heritage.
إنه مثلاً معالم كردية، آثار كردية، اللباس الكردي
Like Kurdish landmarks, Kurdish antiquities, Kurdish
clothing.
يعني بجسدهم بحولهم للوحة فنية يعني، من خلال رسمي ومن خلال
فني، يعني بجسد شي عن الأكراد
I mean, I embody them, I turn them into a painting, through
my drawing and my art. I embody something about the Kurds.
الشيء اللي نحن عم نتعايش معه، بحوله للوحة فنية.
The things we live with, I turn them into a painting.
آخر لوحة هو تجسيد بين معالم كردية وعربية، هي اللوحة لقلعة
صلاح الدين الأيوبي
The latest painting is an embodiment of Kurdish and Arabic
landmarks. This is a painting of the Citadel of Salah al-Din
al-Ayyubi,
ونبي هوري بريف عفرين هو معلم أثري كردي، وفي مسجد الأموي بشام
كمان
and Nabi Houri in the countryside of Afrin, which is a
Kurdish archaeological landmark, and the Umayyad Mosque in
Damascus too.
فحبينا أنا وأنسة تانية معي نجسد هي اللوحة الفنية، نوصل إنه
معالمنا
So, another teacher and I wanted to embody this painting, to
show that our landmarks
يؤدي إلى توحد، توحيد اللوحة يعني ما في فرق بين الكردي أو
العربي
lead to unity, unifying the painting, meaning there is no
difference between a Kurd or an Arab.
حبينا نوصل إنه بيكملوا البعض يعني
We wanted to show that they complement each other.
اللوحات الكردية اللي أنا عم برسمهم هو بشكل عام يعني في إقبال
لهالشي أكيد، عن التراث الكردي أو الزي الكردي أو معالم أثرية
The Kurdish paintings that I draw, in general, there is
definitely demand for them, about Kurdish heritage, Kurdish
dress, or archaeological landmarks.
في منهم بيشتروا، في منهم بهديهم إياهم، يعني في أشخاص معينة
يعني بشكل عام بيتقبلوا هالشي
Some of them buy them, some I gift them to. I mean, certain
people in general appreciate this.
بالعكس يعني تطلع الشيء اللي عندك، أو معلم أثري اللي عندك
واللي بتتعايش معه وطالعه بلوحة فنية أو تبيعه أو تهديه، يعني
هاد الشي كتير منيح.
On the contrary, to bring out what you have, or an
archaeological landmark that you have and live with, and put
it in a painting, or sell it, or gift it, this is a very
good thing.
Tu bi xêr hatî buharê, tu xweşî tu nazdarê
Welcome spring, you are beautiful, you are lovely
Tu mizgîna serê salê, te şîn kir dar û berê
You are the good news of the new year, you made the trees
and surroundings green
Tu mizgîna serê salê, te şîn kir dar û berê
You are the good news of the new year, you made the trees
and surroundings green
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Tu bihara sûr û zer î
You are the red and yellow spring
Wey kuro kuro tac li ser î
Oh boy, boy with a crown on your head
Tu bihara sûr û zer î
You are the red and yellow spring
Wey kuro kuro tac li ser î
Oh boy, boy with a crown on your head
O te porê reş kirye serî
Oh, you put the black hair on your head
Xêr û naliş meye derî
Goodness and groans are at our door
O te porê reş kirye serî
Oh, you put the black hair on your head
Xêr û naliş meye derî
Goodness and groans are at our door
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Di dilê min ax û deşte
In my heart there are sighs and plains
Yarê şuştî rû bi teşt e
The beloved washed her face in the basin
Di dilê min ax û deşte
In my heart there are sighs and plains
Yarê şuştî rû bi teşt e
The beloved washed her face in the basin
Tê rîhan e der sûkê tê
You come as basil to the market
Xefarê dîna qemeran tê
The forgiver of the world comes to the dark ones
Tê rîhan e der sûkê tê
You come as basil to the market
Xefarê dîna qemeran tê
The forgiver of the world comes to the dark ones
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Bi xwarî zêk a şorîn tê
You come down sweet and salty
Delalê kefa wî ran î
Beautiful one, the palm of his thigh
Bi xwarî zêk a şorîn tê
You come down sweet and salty
Delalê kefa wî ran î
Beautiful one, the palm of his thigh
Kemberşalyo bi meş û şişî
With a shawl and walking straight
Dîroka kurdan bi naqişî
You embroider the history of the Kurds
Kemberşalyo bi meş û şişî
With a shawl and walking straight
Dîroka kurdan bi naqişî
You embroider the history of the Kurds
Tu bi xêratî bixwîne
Read with goodness
Kuf û sîtav meste re
Foam and shade, drunkard
Tu bi xêratî bixwîne
Read with goodness
Kuf û sîtav meste re
Foam and shade, drunkard
Tu mizgîniya serê salê
You are the good news of the new year
Te jîn e merdan damar e
You are the life and vein of the brave
Tu mizgîniya serê salê
You are the good news of the new year
Te jîn e merdan damar e
You are the life and vein of the brave
يحاول السيد شادي تعليم الأطفال الموسيقى الكردية
Mr. Shadi is trying to teach children Kurdish music
التي تحمل تراثاً قديماً نقل جيلاً بعد جيل
Which carries an ancient heritage passed down from
generation to generation
وحدثنا عن أهمية الموسيقى والبزق عند الأكراد
He told us about the importance of music and the buzuq among
the Kurds
وعن المقامات التي يتميزون بها.
And the maqams they are distinguished by.
كل شخص بده يعرف عن حاله
Everyone who wants to introduce themselves
بفرجي فلكلوره للعالم.
Shows their folklore to the world.
هداك الوقت كل العالم بيعرف إنه
At that time, the whole world will know
شو هو الفلكلور يعني.
What the folklore is.
شلون بيعيش شلون بيقدم.
How they live, how they present themselves.
آلة البزق هي آلة
The buzuq is an instrument
بالكردي اسمها طنبور.
In Kurdish, its name is tembûr.
وأكثر شيء بيعزفوا عالبزق يعني
And mostly they play the buzuq, I mean
يعني الدارج بين الأكراد هو البزق يعني
I mean, the popular one among Kurds is the buzuq
غيره، بعض منهم بيستعملوا الأورغ هاي هي.
Besides that, some of them use the keyboard, that's it.
أكثر شي الدبكات الشعبية
Mostly popular dabkes
بيدبكوا رقصات شعبية هي هي.
They dance popular dances, that's it.
مثلا متل المقسوم، إيقاع مقسوم، بلدي
For example, like Maqsum, Maqsum rhythm, Baladi
لف، جورجينا.
Laff, Georgina.
أكثر شي هالدبكات مشهورين فيها.
They are mostly famous for these dabkes.
أكثر شي بالأغاني
Mostly in songs
أغانيهم طبعاً أكثر شي بيجي مقام الكرد
Their songs, of course, mostly come in the Kurd maqam
والحجاز والبيات.
And Hijaz and Bayat.
أكثر شي بيغنوا على هالأغاني
They mostly sing to these songs
يعني شي بسيط، نادراً قليل بيستعملوا العجم.
I mean something simple, rarely, they use Ajam a little.
هاي بدك تعتبر شلون أغاني الفلسطينيين
This, you can consider how the songs of the Palestinians are
بيكون فيها نكهة الحزن
There is a flavor of sadness in them
الأكراد كمان هيك نفس الفلسطينيين
The Kurds are also the same, like the Palestinians
مضطهدين من هالشي.
Persecuted, from this aspect.
[Muzîk]
[Music]
تعد بلدة الباسوطة من أجمل المناطق في سوريا
The town of Basouta is considered one of the most beautiful
areas in Syria
بلدة عرف أهلها بالكرم وحسن الضيافة
A town whose people are known for generosity and hospitality
عدا عن البساطة والعادات والتقاليد
Aside from the simplicity, customs, and traditions
التي حملوها معهم منذ الأجيال الماضية.
Which they carried with them since past generations.
إلى هنا نكون قد وصلنا لختام حلقتنا لهذا اليوم
Here we have reached the end of our episode for today
نلقاكم في حلقات قادمة
We will see you in upcoming episodes
إلى اللقاء.
Goodbye.
[Muzîk]
[Music]